[{"question":"A cell is bound to divide, if it has entered:","a":"G2-phase","b":"G1-phase ","c":"Prophase ","d":"S-phase ","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"In plants, active mitosis occurs in:","a":"Cambium","b":"Leaf tip","c":"Root base","d":"Mid vein","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"In meiosis, actual haploidy in comes in:  terms of DNA","a":"Metaphase-I","b":"Anaphase-II","c":"Anaphase-I","d":"Interkinesis","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"If the number of bivalents are 8 in metaphase- 1, what shall be the number of chromosomes in daughter cells after meiosis-I and meiosis - II respectively?","a":"8 and 4","b":"4and 4","c":"8and 8","d":"16and 8","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Programmed cell death (apoptosis):","a":"occurs in cells that have been deprived of  (c) Prophase (d) S-phase 2. In plants, active mitosis occurs in:  essential nutrients.","b":"occurs only in cells that have damaged DNA.","c":"is a natural process during development","d":"is signaled by the initiated mitosis","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Number of chromosomes in a zygote may be indicated by ","a":"4x","b":"X","c":"3x","d":"2x","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"At which stage of cell cycle division the  4.  8.  explanation (given in column-II) and choose  homologous chromosome separate, while sister  the correct combination from the options given chromatid remain associated at their centromere","a":"Metaphase-I of meiosis","b":"Anaphase-I of meiosis","c":"Metaphase of mitosis","d":"Anaphase of mitosis","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Identify the given figures (1, 2 & 3) showing  Column-I  Column-11 (Explanation)  (Terms)  A. Terminalization L  . Pairing of  meiotic phases and select the correct option","a":"1-Metaphase 2-Anaphase 3-Telophase   ","b":" 1-Metaphase-II 2-Anaphase-II3-Telophase-II","c":"1-Metaphase-II 2-Anaphase-II3-Telophase-II","d":"1-Anaphase-I 2-Metaphase-I3-Telophase-I","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"During which stages (or prophase I substages) of meiosis do you expect to find the bivalents and DNA replication respectively? Critical ","a":"Pachytene and interphase (between two meiotic division) ","b":"Pachytene and interphase (just prior to prophase 1)","c":"Pachytene and S phase (of interphase just prior to prophase 1) ","d":"Zygotene and S phase (of interphase prior to prophase 1).","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following is correct for the mitotic spindle ?","a":"It is composed of actin and myosin microfilament..","b":"It is composed of kinetochores at the metaphase plate ","c":" It is composed of microtubules, which helpto separate the chromosomes to opposite poles of the cell ","d":"It originates only at the centrioles in the centrosomes  ","hint":"","correct":"b"}]